<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Networks | OJ's perspective]]></title>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/categories/networks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-27T23:36:02+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://buffered.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OJ Reeves]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vote with your Wallet]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/vote-with-your-wallet/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-05T15:13:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/vote-with-your-wallet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="http://buffered.io/posts/living-in-australia-has-a-downside/" title="Living in Australia has a Downside">previous post</a> I had a bit of a combined whinge about MS downloads and bandwidth limits in Australia. Today I read a <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/news/technology/phone-and-broadband-bills-to-rise/posts/1196530678984.html" title="Phone and broadband bills to rise">new article at SMH</a> that made me even more angry.<!--more--></p>

<p>For those who don&rsquo;t know, Australia&rsquo;s broadband/phone network is predominantly owned and controlled by <a href="http://www.telstra.com/" title="Telstra">Telstra</a>. In short, this company is largely responsible for the issues. Not only do they charge insane amounts for their shitty service, they&rsquo;re going to be charging more down the track. The cost of phone line rental is extremely high. Their Internet plans are a joke. The service network is terrible, and just don&rsquo;t even think about getting support over the phone from someone who know&rsquo;s what they&rsquo;re doing.</p>

<p>When I first started looking for a broadband provider back in 2003, I decided to avoid Telstra because their plans didn&rsquo;t seem to be as competitive as others. Instead, I decided to go with a company that I am actually using now (<a href="http://www.internode.on.net/" title="Internode">Internode</a>). The process of signing up looked to be fairly simple, so I filled in the online form and away we went.</p>

<p>About 2 days later I was informed by Internode that they weren&rsquo;t able to provision a connection on my phone line for some wierd reason. They told me that the issue is with Telstra, because they own the line, and that I should give them a call to find out what the problem is.</p>

<p>Upon calling Telstra I was told that they weren&rsquo;t able to help me. They said that they had a reason for rejecting the connection request, but they would consider looking into the problem if, and only if, I signed up with <em>them</em> and not Internode.</p>

<p>I was stunned! In no so many words, the lady on the other end of the phone had basically said that if I sign up with Telstra I&rsquo;d get a connection, but I&rsquo;d be rejected if I went through Internode. I decided to stick with dial-up rather than give them my cash.</p>

<p>Thankfully things have now changed, and I no longer live in a spot where there are issues on the line. But that at least gives you an idea of what Telstra is like to deal with. From what I&rsquo;ve heard, these days they&rsquo;re even worse.</p>

<p>The idea of them winning the tender to sort out the Internet infrastructure in this country just gives me the shivers. I mean, they say it themselves:<blockquote><p>Just this week Telstra&rsquo;s public policy chief, Phil Burgess, admitted the company&rsquo;s strategy was to become a &ldquo;premium provider charging premium prices&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>That&rsquo;s straight from the horses mouth! If that&rsquo;s not enough evidence, check this out:<blockquote><p>Telstra will not want to reduce margins because it has promised shareholders it will increase the company&rsquo;s overall pre-tax profit margins from 42 per cent to between 46 and 48 per cent by 2010.</p></blockquote>Are they thinking about the consumer? Hell no. It&rsquo;s all about bleeding you dry.</p>

<p>Something needs to be done. I&rsquo;m voting with my wallet, and telling Telstra to go f**k themselves by signing up with a competitor. You can do the same. Right now I&rsquo;m looking for ways to completely remove myself from any of Telstra&rsquo;s services and I know I&rsquo;ll feel better for doing it.</p>

<p>I think you will too :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living in Australia has a Downside]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/living-in-australia-has-a-downside/"/>
    <updated>2007-11-21T08:04:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/living-in-australia-has-a-downside</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This may come as a surprise, but living in Australia <em>can</em> have it downsides :) Right now I can only think of one, and that&rsquo;s (part of) the reason for this post.</p>

<p>We may have constant sunshine, lovely beaches and a lifestyle to die for, but our broadband just <strong>sucks</strong>. That&rsquo;s a fairly sweeping statement, so let me clarify a little more.</p>

<p>Broadband plans in this country are <em>extremely</em> poor value. The service that you receive for the amount you pay is substandard. It&rsquo;s that simple. Those of you in places like the UK, USA and Hong Kong may find it obscure to consider that a country exists where you can&rsquo;t get an unlimited data connection for DSL. You may also find it difficult to believe that some connection speeds are cut to that of a dial-up connection if you download too much. But that&rsquo;s exactly what happens here.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>These days in Australia most ISPs provide a limited download quota per month for a set fee. What happens when you download too much will vary from provider to provider. Many of the providers simply cut your download speed so that it feels like you&rsquo;re back on a dialup modem. Others simply charge per MB or GB that you go over (and they&rsquo;re not cheap either!). What&rsquo;s &ldquo;nice&rdquo; about the latter option is that many of these ISPs don&rsquo;t actually let you know that you&rsquo;ve gone over quota. So instead of being warned, you just cop a huge bill at the end of the month. Yes, I believe it&rsquo;s your job to monitor your bandwidth usage, but that&rsquo;s still pretty shoddy.</p>

<p>Every 6 months or so I have another look around to see if I can find another provider that will offer me more than what I currently have. Right now I have a connection through <a href="http://www.internode.on.net/" title="Internode">Internode</a>. They provide me with an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ADSL" title="ADSL">ADSL</a> connection at 1.5mbps/256kbps with 10GB download per month. If I go over that my speed is &ldquo;shaped&rdquo; to 64kbps/64kbps. All of this is delivered down my copper wire for the princly sum of AUD $54.95 per month. No, that doesn&rsquo;t include the cost of having a phone line in the first place.</p>

<p>In day to day life for me this is actually adequate. I don&rsquo;t download too much stuff, and most of my browsing (and the wife&rsquo;s) is fairly light on the bandwidth. But every now and then I feel the pinch and the frustration that comes with my plan&hellip;  <ul><li><strong>Windows Updates.</strong> I&rsquo;m sure that every user of Windows is aware of the joys of constant updates from Microsoft. Some of them are small, some of them are absolutley <em>massive</em>. Multiply these updates by the number of computers in your home, and you&rsquo;ve got quite a hit on the quota.</li><li><strong>Linux Updates.</strong> I just happend to dual-boot Windows XP x64 with <a href="http://www.linuxmint.com/" title="Linux Mint">Linux Mint</a>, and so I have the added benefit of constant updates through that as well. Thankfully I can pick and choose what I want updated, and most of the time the updates are reasonably small (<em>and</em> they don&rsquo;t force me to reboot my machine).</li><li><strong>Steam.</strong> I have a <a href="http://www.steampowered.com/" title="Steam">Steam</a> account which I use to buy pretty much all the games that I play (which aren&rsquo;t many). Most games these days are also bloody massive. Get yourself a copy of Bioshock and Half-Life 2, and you&rsquo;ve nearly blown your monthly quota away. Add to that the updates to the Steam platform, and some of the media/demos you can get for free, and your quota begins to look pitiful.</li><li><strong>Development.</strong> Yes, I&rsquo;m a Geek. I write code. I need tools. I need to keep up to speed. I have a subscription to things like <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/msdn/" title="MSDN">MSDN</a> so I can get access to this stuff. Everything that I need has to be <em>downloaded</em> and hence is yet another huge hit on the download quota.</li></ul>There&rsquo;s obviously some motivation for this post, and strangley enough it&rsquo;s due to the bandwidth issue <em>and</em> MSDN.</p>

<p>Those of you who are reading this are probably geeks too. So you&rsquo;ll know that recently Microsoft decided to release <a href="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/vstudio/products/aa700831.aspx" title="Visual Studio 2008">Visual Studio 2008</a> which comes with all the creamy goodness of .NET 3.5 and C# 3.0. Not only was I interested in getting this because I wanted to play with it, but I <em>needed</em> it for work. So a download was required (all 3.31GB of it).</p>

<p>Initially I thought I&rsquo;d download the disc image while I was at work. I started the download off yesterday morning when I got into the office only to find &hellip; work suffers from download quotas issues just like the rest of us! It appeared that our bandwidth quota had been blown, and the download speed was being shaped (ie. I was getting a massive 1.2Kb/s off microsoft.com, not good for a 3.31GB download).</p>

<p>Fair enough, I know what that&rsquo;s all about. So I decided to wait til I get home and fire the download off on my home machine over night. When I got home I jumped on MSDN, fired up the download and away it went at 160Kb/s! SWEET! Shame we&rsquo;re stuck using the stupid MSDN downloader application, but hey, it appears to support resuming of downloads so if anything goes wrong I can simply kick it off again and it&rsquo;ll resume from where it left off.</p>

<p>I think you can see where this is going. Before I say any more I&rsquo;d like to ask a key question: Why is it that all downloads die at 99%?</p>

<p>I got up this morning and quickly checked to see if the download had finished. To my dismay, it had reached 99% and then thrown up an error message. I don&rsquo;t have the exact wording handy, but it essentially said:<blockquote><p>The download died for some unknown reason. Give it another go.</p></blockquote>So I hit the resume button with a huge grin, thinking that it was just going to carry on nicely, only to find that MS had slapped me in the face&hellip;<blockquote><p>The file no longer exists on the server. I can&rsquo;t resume. Press X to delete everything you&rsquo;ve downloaded so far, Press Y otherwise.</p></blockquote>I pounced on Y and was grateful to find that the majority of the download was still on disk. I thought I&rsquo;d go back to MSDN downloads to kick the download off again from the start, and try some geek trickery to get it to think that the imgae I&rsquo;d already downloaded was the one I had just started. When I return to MSDN, I find that the link for Visual Studio 2008 Professional constantly redirects back to another page. I wasn&rsquo;t able to get to the same download page to start the download off again and grab that last 1%. Just when I thought it couldn&rsquo;t get any worse&hellip;</p>

<p>&hellip; the downloader closed. Without me asking it to. And with it, it took all 99% of that 3.31GB that I had downloaded.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t tell you exactly what I said, but I can tell you it wasn&rsquo;t pretty. Various expletives flew around the room, generally in the direction of MS and their stupid downloader. Then I realised that I&rsquo;d blown well over 3GB of my 10GB download per month and achieved absolutely nothing. It was at this poin I hurled abuse at Internode for having such a shitty selection of plans.</p>

<p>After calming down I realised that it wasn&rsquo;t so bad. It could be worse.</p>

<p>&hellip; I could be living in the UK! :D</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
