<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Freeware | OJ's rants]]></title>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/categories/freeware/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-30T20:08:50+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://buffered.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OJ Reeves]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Be Part of a World Record]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/be-part-of-a-world-record/"/>
    <updated>2008-05-31T11:29:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/be-part-of-a-world-record</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.spreadfirefox.com/node&id=0&t=272"><img border="0" alt="Download Day - English" title="Download Day - English" src="http://www.spreadfirefox.com/files/images/affiliates_banners/468x60_ddayb_en.png"/></a>
Get yourself a copy of Firefox 3 on the day it's released <a href="http://www.spreadfirefox.com/en-US/worldrecord/" title="Firefox 3">from this site</a> and you'll be doing your bit to get Firefox downloads in the world record books.</p>

<p>Yup, you'll also be falling for a huge marketing gag designed to get Firefox installed on as many machines as possible, but it's a damned good browser anyway, so no harm done! :)</p>

<div style="clear: both; float: none;"></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rancid Bloatware]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/rancid-bloatware/"/>
    <updated>2007-11-01T12:53:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/rancid-bloatware</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'd love to know what on earth got into <a href="http://www.adobe.com/" title="Adobe">Adobe's</a> head when they decided to turn their <a href="http://www.adobe.com/products/reader/" title="Adobe Reader">PDF reader</a> into a stinking pile of sluggish bloatware? Who here remembers the old days when the Adobe Reader download was less than 10MB?</p>

<p>Take a look at the details on their current <a href="http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html" title="Reader Download">download page</a> (which I was recently forced to visit because of a <a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/posts/new_gozi_strain/print.html" title="New Strain of Gozi Trojan Prowls the Net">security flaw</a> in the Reader's functionality that has now been patched):</p>

<!--more-->


<blockquote><p><b>New Adobe Reader 8
</b><ul><li>Work <i>smarter</i> - a clean new look, custom toolbars and an RSS reader</li><li>Work <i>faster</i> - 2D acceleration (requires video card support, Win only)</li><li>Work <i>together</i> - new online conferencing with Acrobat Connect</li></p></blockquote>


<p>WTF? I want a simple, fast PDF reader...<ul><li>Do I want custom toolbars? Actually, no, I don't. I want a single standard one with a few helpful buttons, and that's it.</li><li>Do I want an RSS reader? <strong>HELL NO!</strong> Give me a SMALL download. If I want a local RSS reader, I'll go grab one. Otherwise I'll stick to tools like <a href="http://www.google.com/reader/view/" title="Google Reader">Google Reader</a>.</li><li>Do I want online conferencing from a bloody PDF viewer? No, I most certainly do not.</li></ul>I don't see the reasoning behind all this crap. It's another example of software going off the rails. The authors are just trying to squeeze in too many features. A PDF reader is <em>not</em> a platform for collaboration or communication. It should render a document for me to read. That's about it. What makes it worse is that they claim it to be fast, but it's not!</p>

<p>On top of this, you have to have some shitty little Adobe Agent running all the time, which undoubtedly gives this application the "amazing speed" they seem to be talking about.</p>

<p>For another kick in the nuts, they require you to <strong>reboot</strong> your machine after installation! Oh. My. God. Why?!</p>

<p>Here's the icing on the cake...<blockquote><p>Adobe Reader 8.1.1 - 22.3MB</p></blockquote>Holy crap. <em>22.3MB</em>!! What a joke. That's an obscenely large download for a document viewer. People wonder why I stick to <a href="http://www.foxitsoftware.com/pdf/rd_intro.php" title="Foxit Software">Foxit Reader</a>?! It's fast, it has all the functionality I need, and it's only <u>2.1MB</u>. That's what we need more of. Software that's small, functional and hits a point of pain, nothing more.</p>

<p>So, other than the obvious candidates (Windows, Norton Product Suite, etc) what bloatware have you suffered lately?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gadget Me Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/gadget-me-up/"/>
    <updated>2006-11-08T06:13:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/gadget-me-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don't know if you guys are free software gadget monkeys or not, but this stuff might be of value to those of you who use Visual Studio 2005.  The guys over at <a href="http://www.slickedit.com/" title="SlickEdit" target="_blank">SlickEdit.com</a>, makers of the top notch SlickEdit editor, have released a stack of free <a href="http://www.slickedit.com/content/view/441" title="SlickEdit - SlickEdit Gadgets for Microsoft Visual Studio 2005" target="_blank">gadgets for Visual Studio 2005</a> which are free! (I love that word.. I'm going to say it again.. FREEEEE).</p>

<p>The freebies include:</p>

<ul><li>Editor Gadgets (Line ruler, Indentation guide, Auto-copy selection, Editor Graphic)</li><li>The Command Spy</li><li>File Explorer</li><li>Data Object Analyser</li><li>The SLOC Report</li></ul>


<p>It's a nice collection of tools if you ask me! Well worth playing with, so feel free to head over there and get your copy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FireFox 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/firefox-2/"/>
    <updated>2006-10-24T12:48:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/firefox-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://getfirefox.com/" title="Get Firefox - Web browsing redefined." target="_blank"><img class="InlineImageRight" src="http://www.mozilla.org/products/firefox/buttons/getfirefox_large2.png" width="178" height="60" border="0" alt="Get Firefox"></a>WAHOO! It's been released :) Our lovable browser has had its second major version <a href="http://www.theinquirer.net/default.aspx?article=35284" title="Don't wait for Firefox Numero Duo" target="_blank">released into the wild</a>, which is great news. I've been using the latest released candidate for a while, and have had no issues at all, but now it's officially out there for all to enjoy.</p>

<p>Point your currently insecure/outdated browsers over <a href="http://releases.mozilla.org/pub/mozilla.org/firefox/releases/2.0/" title="Mozilla Releases" target="_blank">here</a> and start your download.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Real-Time Flight Monitoring]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/real-time-flight-monitoring/"/>
    <updated>2006-10-05T19:45:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/real-time-flight-monitoring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a read of Eastabrook's blog recently (see a link in the Blogroll) and noticed that he posted about an interesting link that he found.  The link, entitled <a href="http://www.fboweb.com/antest/ge/intro.aspx?old=1" title="Flight Tracking in 3D" target="_blank">Flight Tracking in 3D</a>, shows details of a few downloads that you can grab for <a href="http://earth.google.com/" title="Google Earth" target="_blank">Google Earth</a> which actually show the current locations of <strong>flights that are currently in progress all over the world!!!</strong></p>

<p>Unbelievable. Pretty amazing technology, and at the same time quite scary. What kind of possible security issues does this feature open up?  I know that Google Earth has had these kinds of questions asked in the past, but this to me seems like it's taking the issue to a whole new level.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
