<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ruby on Rails | OJ's rants]]></title>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/categories/ruby-on-rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-11T21:47:11+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://buffered.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OJ Reeves]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.NET MVC]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/net-mvc/"/>
    <updated>2007-03-28T17:15:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/net-mvc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Isn't it amazing how life can just hit turbo without prior warning, and your time seems to just disappear!  I need to find some way of sticking blogging back into my routine :)</p>

<p>For the last couple of weeks I've been playing around a fair bit with <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/" title="Ruby" target="_blank">Ruby</a> and <a href="http://www.rubyonrails.org/" title="Ruby on Rails" target="_blank">Rails</a>.  I've been having a great deal of fun at the same time, and I recommend it to any of you who are thinking of taking up some of your own time with learning web development.  It's really good fun, it's interesting, and it's a great platform for building web apps on.  Sure it has its pitfalls (as do all web development options), but it's a worthy contender and it's only going to get better.  More on that in another post ;)</p>

<p>The reason I mentioned it is because of the news that ASP.NET has an <a href="http://codebetter.com/blogs/jeffrey.palermo/archive/posts/Big-News-_2D00_-MVC-framework-for-ASP.NET-in-the-works-_2D00_-level-300.aspx">MVC framework in the works</a>, which looks like it's going to be very similar to the way Rails works.  I think this is a good thing as it'll force people to move away from an (possibly) unnecessary <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/msdnmag/issues/06/08/DesignPatterns/default.aspx" title="MVP" target="_blank">MVP</a> approach (for most things) and work with a well-structured <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model-view-controller" title="MVC" target="_blank">MVC</a> (which a surprising amount of developers don't yet know about!).</p>

<p>No doubt this is another effort by Microsoft to rip off some code from <a href="http://www.castleproject.org/monorail/index.html" title="MonoRail" target="_blank">another established project</a> and claim it as their own, but still if it works and works well, then I'm not really complaining.</p>

<p>Anyway, what do you guys think? Is this a good or a bad thing?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
