<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mac OS | OJ's perspective]]></title>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/categories/mac-os/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-15T18:09:14+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://buffered.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OJ Reeves]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Irssi and SASL on OSX]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/irssi-and-sasl-on-osx/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-03T08:37:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/irssi-and-sasl-on-osx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Given my renewed focus on security I've been looking to lock down much of my communications so that I <em>feel</em> more secure online. One of the things that I use quite a lot to connect with people who know WTF they're talking about is IRC. <a href="https://freenode.net/" title="Freenode IRC network">#freenode</a> is my network of choice as it has a bunch of interesting places with fairly active communities. <a href="http://www.irssi.org/" title="irssi IRC client">irssi</a> is my current client of choice for a few reasons.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simple_Authentication_and_Security_Layer" title="SASL">SASL</a>, among other things, is one thing that can be enabled to secure your communication on IRC. There's quite a bit of information out there already about how to <a href="https://freenode.net/sasl/sasl-irssi.shtml" title="Enabling SASL in irssi on Freenode">enable SASL for irssi on Freenode</a>. These instructions worked out of the box for me on Linux, but not on Mac OSX. After downloading <code>cap_sasl.pl</code> and putting it in <code>~/.irssi/scripts/autorun</code> and installing the required Perl modules I went through the steps to get SASL configured. When I attempted to enable it as per the instructions using the command <code>/sasl set network TheColonial &lt;password&gt; DH-BLOWFISH</code> I had the following error:</p>

<blockquote><p>Can't locate object method "send_raw_now" via package "Irssi::Irc::Server"</p></blockquote>

<p>This took a bit of Googling to nail. It turns out that, for some reason, on Mac OSX <code>irssi</code> actually requires an extra package to be included in the script. So open <code>cap_sasl.pl</code> and look for this (it's right at the top):</p>

<pre><code>use strict;
use Irssi;
</code></pre>

<p>Immediately below this, add the following:</p>

<pre><code>use Irssi::Irc;
</code></pre>

<p>The script should now run fine and <code>irssi</code> should stop complaining.</p>

<p>This might seem obvious to some, but it wasn't to me! From what I can tell other people around the traps have had the same problem so I thought I'd post this in the hope that it helps others.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What About Going the Other Way?]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/what-about-going-the-other-way/"/>
    <updated>2006-10-19T20:02:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/what-about-going-the-other-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just thought I'd add this last post as a bit of food for thought before signing off today. This link comes from a bloke who's been through the pain of wanting to move away from Windows, only to find that the results were just as, if not more, painful than sticking to what he knew. Have a read of <a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~bederson/user-advocate/2006/09/switchback-horrors-of-windows-power.html" title="HCI User Advocate: Switchback: Horrors of a Windows Power-user Trying to Switch to Apple OS X" target="_blank">this blog entry</a> to see that the grass isn't necessarily greener.</p>

<p>It definitely makes you wonder if the effort is going to be worth it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Virtual Vista Stuff-Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/virtual-vista-stuff-up/"/>
    <updated>2006-10-17T08:33:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/virtual-vista-stuff-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OK, so it looks like I might have been misinformed (er... wrong :)) by stating that the basic versions of Vista can't be installed on VMs. That'll teach me not to read the licencing details properly myself! It looks like it was a slight misunderstanding of the terms and structure that MS used in stating the rules. I won't go into the details myself since <a href="http://blogs.zdnet.com/Bott/?p=157" title="No, theres no ban on virtual Vista" target="_blank">Ed Bott has already done it for me</a>. So, MS <em>haven't</em> shot themselves in the foot in this regard, but they still seem to be doing it in other ways.</p>

<p>One of those ways, which is now 100% confirmed, is that you can only move your installation of Vista to a different machine (read: different hardware) <strong>once and once <em>only</em></strong>. Again, this is confirmed courtesty of <a href="http://blogs.zdnet.com/Bott/?p=156" title="A sneaky change in Windows licensing terms" target="_blank">Ed Bott</a>. Instead of being able to reinstall when you buy a new mobo, and then reinstall again after you buy a new CPU, you may well have to fork out for another Vista licence due to the hardware change. What a lovely feature!</p>

<p>Yesterday's chat (via previous post on Vista) with Bryce got me thinking about what other peoples' thoughts were regarding the whole stance MS are taking with Vista, and during my searches I found <a href="http://www.computerpoweruser.com/editorial/article.asp?article=articles/archive/c0611/44c11/44c11.asp&guid=8CF5E5CB35CB42E1857F6F42970E2A2C" title="Vista Will Double Apples Market Share" target="_blank">this post by Chris Pirillo</a> (a long-time MS user) which covers his views on said topic. It's quite an interesting read :) He also took a bit of time to post on his blog after writing the article to cover some <a href="http://chris.pirillo.com/posts/microsoft-windows-vista-vs-apple-os-x/" title="Microsoft Windows Vista vs. Apple OS X" target="_blank">other points</a>, again well worth reading.  It's good to see another long-term MS user with the balls to speak out loud and say that Macs are becoming more appealing by the day.  I agree with him when he says that MS isn't really making this a difficult decision to make.</p>

<p>I've never been a huge fan of Macs, partly because I never had to use them and Windows was familiar, but as time goes by I'm rethinking my position. I keep saying that there's not enough software out there for me to make the move to Mac (and Linux), but not I'm thinking that I need to make the switch and become one of the developers that can help sort that problem out :D</p>

<p>So, sorry about my stuff up, but it doesn't really improve my view of Vista by much anyway!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
