<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Hardware | OJ's perspective]]></title>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/categories/hardware/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-25T21:15:26+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://buffered.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OJ Reeves]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Regrets]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/no-regrets/"/>
    <updated>2008-04-12T21:49:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/no-regrets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is just a brief follow-up to my <a href="http://buffered.io/posts/another-new-keyboard/" title="Another New Keyboard">previous post</a> on the keyboard I bought.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve now had the chance to use it a fair bit, and I thought I&rsquo;d give you a small summary based on my experience.</p>

<ul><li>It rocks.</li>
<li>It's better than I had hoped.</li>
<li>It is sex on a stick.</li></ul>


<p>Buy one. Now.</p>

<p>That is all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another New Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/another-new-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2008-03-28T21:33:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/another-new-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A little while ago I <a href="http://buffered.io/posts/a-hardware-update/" title="A Hardware Update">posted</a> about some new hardware that I bought. In that update I mentioned that I&rsquo;d bought a new keyboard because my old one was a bit shaky and had the old UK layout which was no longer valid since I have now returned to Australia.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The keyboard that I bought, a <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/hardware/mouseandkeyboard/productdetails.aspx?pid=043">Microsoft Natural Ergonomic 4000</a>, was one that I had seen recommended on a few sites. I was told that the keyboard was good to use, was comfy, and that it was quiet. After reading the reviews I decided to take the plunge.</p>

<p>Since buying that keyboard, I&rsquo;ve barely touched my desktop computer. <em>That</em> is how much I disliked the keyboard. Instead I stuck with my laptop. My pokey, slow, Vista-infected laptop rather than my dual-screen, dual-boot desktop. Sure it was comfy as far as the hands were concerned, but the layout just didn&rsquo;t feel right. It could be that I&rsquo;m too used to having to use the standard keyboards that the ergonomic ones just don&rsquo;t feel right. On top of that, the issue of the <strong>incredibly noisy spacebar</strong> was one that I just couldn&rsquo;t get past. The rest of the keyboard was relatively quiet, but that damned spacebar required approximately 150N of force applied to it before the damned thing would budge. Silicon lubricant did nothing. The only way to make it budge was to hit it, and hit it hard. Needless to say, it was uncomfortable and <em>very</em> noisy.</p>

<p>For the sake of this discussion, I won&rsquo;t go into detail about the extra keys which were really tacky. Let&rsquo;s just say they sucked, and they felt flimsy.</p>

<p>I went back to the drawing board and started researching again. This time I came across a keyboard that took my eye straight away. One that was recommended by another mate, and a man who updates his hardware more often than anyone I&rsquo;ve ever met (you know who you are ;)). Again, I did some reading and decided to take the plunge &ndash; scared that I might end up making the same mistake.</p>

<p><a href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2008/03/2007951535362581.jpg" title="Enermax Aurora Premium" rel="lightbox[enermax]"><img src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2008/03/2007951535362581.jpg" alt="Enermax Aurora Premium" style="float: left; padding-right: 3px; padding-bottom: 3px; border: 0;" width="120" /></a>I didn&rsquo;t. This keyboard is a dream. It&rsquo;s saved my desktop machine from total banishment! My saviour: the <a href="http://www.enermaxusa.com/catalog/product_info.php?cPath=28_48&products_id=137" title="Enermax Aurora KB007U Premium">Enermax Aurora KB007U Premium</a>.</p>

<p>Make no mistake, ladies and gentlemen, this keyboard will make you feel like you&rsquo;ve died and gone to heaven. I could spend hours and hours dribbling on about how this keyboard makes me happy downstairs, but instead I&rsquo;ll try and sum it up in these few points.
<a href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2008/03/20079515381429142.gif" title="Enermax Aurora Premium - Closeup" rel="lightbox[enermax]"><img src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2008/03/20079515381429142.gif" alt="Enermax Aurora Premium - Closeup" style="float: right; padding-left: 3px; padding-bottom: 3px; border: 0;" width="120" /></a><ol><li>Brushed aluminium keyboard &ndash; nice and heavy. You will not see this keyboard moving around the desktop as you try to type. It&rsquo;s also nice and cool on the hands.</li><li>Tactile response on the keys is just fantastic, and is incredibly quiet. The act of typing is a joy.</li><li>Standard layout &ndash; no keys added or removed. They&rsquo;re exactly where they should be.</li><li>USB 2.0. Say no more :) Nice and responsive.</li><li>Just so happens to come with a USB 2.0 hub as well. This will definitely get some use!</li><li>Also comes with audio jacks for those people who feel the need to use them &ndash; this isn&rsquo;t something I&rsquo;ll be using, but it&rsquo;s a nice to have feature.</li></ol>Seriously, I can&rsquo;t begin to say how happy I am that I have this keyboard.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re in the market for a new keyboard, and you&rsquo;ve got the dosh, make sure you invest in one of these. You won&rsquo;t regrest it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Hardware Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/a-hardware-update/"/>
    <updated>2008-01-04T23:48:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/a-hardware-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I mentioned in a previous post, I have been getting tired of the keyboard that I have at home. I&rsquo;ve had it since December 2004, and it&rsquo;s well past its use-by date. I bought it while living in the UK and hence it has the UK keyboard layout. This was fine while I <em>lived</em> in the UK, but has been a nuisance since being back in Australia. Every other keyboard that I use has the US layout. So every time I come home I end up making mistakes while typing because keys aren&rsquo;t where my head thinks they are! Aside from the layout issue, some keys were starting to get a bit dodgey and were failing to recognise keypresses.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Today I finally replaced it. I invested in a new <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/hardware/mouseandkeyboard/productdetails.aspx?pid=043" title="Microsoft Natural Ergonomic 4000">Microsoft Natural Ergonomic 4000</a> keyboard which feels really comfortable. In the past I&rsquo;ve avoided these funky shaped keyboards as they haven&rsquo;t really felt right, but this one really does feel good. It has a stack of extra features and buttons, and I think it&rsquo;ll have a well-deserved existence on my desktop. The keys are nice and quiet, and they don&rsquo;t seem to struggle to register like the old one did (a good sign for a new keyboard I know ;)).</p>

<p>There is but one small issue &ndash; the space bar. While the other keys are just fine, the space bar is one noisy key. It dishes out quite a clunk each time it&rsquo;s pushed. The reason for this is that if I don&rsquo;t push it hard enough the bugger won&rsquo;t godown (see, there&rsquo;s a classic example of it). To get it to push down, I have to hit it quite hard and that&rsquo;s where the noise is coming from. Right now I&rsquo;m a little concerned about it, and I&rsquo;m hoping that it&rsquo;ll get quieter and less noisy as it &ldquo;wears in&rdquo;.</p>

<p>While I was shopping I thought I may as well fix a couple of other issues that I have mentioned in my other post about <a href="http://buffered.io/posts/reactivate-again/" title="Reactivate? AGAIN?!">activation</a>.</p>

<p>First of all I now have a new stick of RAM, so I&rsquo;m back up to 1GB. Unfortunately I can&rsquo;t go any higher due to my borked motherboard, but it&rsquo;ll do for now. There is a noticable difference in speed now that I&rsquo;m back up to that amount.</p>

<p>Next up I bought some more <a href="http://www.articsilver.com/as5.htm" title="Artic Silver">Artic Silver</a> thermal grease. I was informed a while back by a mate (Marc) that I&rsquo;d botched the grease job on my GPU and hence the temps were stupidly high. So I&rsquo;ve grabbed some more of this stuff to fix it up. I&rsquo;ll get to that over the weekend, and hopefully we&rsquo;ll see an improvement in GPU temperatures.</p>

<p>Lastly, I bought a new webcam. I did have a <a href="http://www.logitech.com/index.cfm/480/3378&cl=au,en" title="Logitech QuickCam Messenger">Logitech QuickCam Messenger</a>, but it was basically a pile of shit because:<ol><li>The image quality was awful.</li><li>It didn&rsquo;t work on Vista.</li><li>It didn&rsquo;t work on x64.</li><li>It didn&rsquo;t work on Linux.</li></ol>I did a bit of research, and ended up buying a <a href="http://au.creative.com/products/product.asp?category=218&subcategory=219&product=15969&listby=" title="Creative WebCam Vista">Creative WebCam Vista</a>, which has nothing to do with Microsoft&rsquo;s Vista. For AUD $20 you seriously can&rsquo;t go wrong. The camera is a fantastic purchase and does everything I need it to!</p>

<p>On the whole I&rsquo;m happy with my purchases. I just hope this damned space bar doesn&rsquo;t ruin it all!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reactivate? AGAIN!?]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/reactivate-again/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-27T12:29:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/reactivate-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is just a quick post to say how much Microsoft and their draconian OS licensing mechanism are pissing me off right now.</p>

<p>Last week my computer stopped booting. I didn&rsquo;t get around to looking at it until a few days ago because I had visitors over from the UK. Not just that, it is Christmas, and the last thing you want to be doing on your Christmas break is to be fixing computers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I spent an hour or two playing with bits and pieces to try and determine the error. The problem was that the third <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DIMM" title="DIMM">DIMM</a> slot on <a href="http://us.dfi.com.tw/Product/xx_product_spec_details_r_us.jsp?PRODUCT_ID=4556&CATEGORY_TYPE=LP%20UT&SITE=NA" title="DFI Lanparty CFX3200-DR">my motherboard</a> (which, incidentally, has been a bit of a nightmare since I bought it) is dodgey. I removed a 512MB RAM stick from the offending slot over to slot two and the machine started to come alive again. I was pretty happy about this, despite the reduction in RAM speed due to the configuration, since I didn&rsquo;t need to buy anything to make it work again!</p>

<p>So I left the machine for a couple of days again as I was happy with what I achieved. But today, because the study was in a bit of a state due to the bits of computers, manuals, and various other things I&rsquo;d strewn around the room while investigating, I thought I&rsquo;d finalise everything and tidy up.</p>

<p>Since my computer case was open, I thought I&rsquo;d do a bit of housekeeping. I wasn&rsquo;t really happy with the way it was laid out inside so I thought I&rsquo;d tidy that up a bit first. I removed <a href="http://www.linksys.com/servlet/Satellite?c=L_Product_C2&childpagename=US%2FLayout&cid=1150490054358&pagename=Linksys%2FCommon%2FVisitorWrapper" title="Linksys WMP54G">my WLAN card</a> because it was flaky at best in 64-bit, and I&rsquo;d had enough of the lag spikes (time to go back to cabled LAN). I moved <a href="http://www.hisdigital.com/html/product_ov.php?id=217" title="HIS Radeon x1900xtx">my video card</a> to a different slot to create a bit more space between it and <a href="http://www.scythe-usa.com/product/cpu/006/scnj1000p.html" title="Ninja Scythe">my HSF</a> (which is awesome, and does a great job even if it is a behemoth!). I also adjusted the fans a bit, cleaned up a lot of the dust, and moved a few of the cables around to improve air-flow.</p>

<p>So with all that done, I fired up the machine.</p>

<p>.. and got nothing. <strong>Shit</strong>.</p>

<p>The investigation started again. I thought that I&rsquo;d go right for the previous culprit and rip out the RAM stick that I&rsquo;d moved to see if that would resolve the problem. Thankfully, it did. So right now I&rsquo;m running on 1/2GB RAM, not ideal to say the least but the machine is booting which is a lot better than it not.</p>

<p>The machine booted, and up came windows. It was at this point that I remember it telling me that a few days back it wanted me to reactivate Windows because of a <em>substantial change in hardware</em>. Of course, I ignored this stupid box because at the time I hadn&rsquo;t changed <strong>anything</strong>. I&rsquo;d <em>moved a RAM stick</em>!</p>

<p>But today, it greeted me again. This time the message was different. In essense, my 3-day &ldquo;window&rdquo; of reactivation had expired, and I was being forced to reactivate it now. And I do mean <strong>now</strong>. Now as in right now before I was allowed to log on. Oh, but there&rsquo;s a problem here you see, because prior to logging on, there&rsquo;s no network connection. So when you try and activate Windows before logging on, it can&rsquo;t activate over the Interweb because it can&rsquo;t get to it. Of course, the activation fails. But does it let me log in? No. What does it do? I ties itself into an infinite loop of &hellip;<ol><li>Try to log in.</li><li>Fail because it&rsquo;s not activated.</li><li>Try to activate.</li><li>Fail to activate because it&rsquo;s not logged in and hence can&rsquo;t connect.</li><li>Goto step 1.</li></ol>Not happy. Not happy at all. Not only had I <strong>not</strong> changed any hardware in the system (all I&rsquo;d done is move it around, and remove a WLAN card) to force the reactivation, I am now stuck with a machine that won&rsquo;t let me log in. Nice eh?</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a nice little side-note for the Linux fanboys :) (yes, you know who you are). For yonks, a slight modification in anything to do with the video hardware in my machine would result in my linux graphics setup shitting itself. I&rsquo;d then have to spend a chunk of the day trying to get it to work again with my dual-screen setup. But not this time. I&rsquo;d mucked around with everything inside the machine, and what happened when I booted Linux??</p>

<p>Wait for it&hellip; WAIT FOR IT!</p>

<p>Nothing. It booted as if nothing had changed. Video settings were the same. Dual-screen worked. I sat here a little stunned for a while and I was brought back from my daze by the little blinking icon in the system tray telling me that I had updates to download. The network had connected, and everything was sweet.</p>

<p>See that Microsoft? Right there. <strong>That</strong> is what <em>should</em> happen. Nothing more, nothing less. When I reboot after a hardware change, I expect you to continue as if nothing had happened. I expect the network to connect without me dicking with it. I expect a nice little &ldquo;Hello OJ, you legend, how else can I make your life easy today?&rdquo;</p>

<p>So hats off to you <a href="http://www.linuxmint.com/" title="LinuxMint">LinuxMint</a>. You made my day! Now, if only you hadn&rsquo;t borked my Firefox install :) Time to update you to the last version me thinks, and give you a bit of the love and attention that you deserve.</p>

<p>As a final note, it looks like I&rsquo;m going to have to buy some new RAM, and while I&rsquo;m there I&rsquo;m going to ditch this UK keyboard as it has been driving me nuts for the last year and half. Time to get back to the Aussie (some might say US) layout.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Quiet Purchase]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/a-quiet-purchase/"/>
    <updated>2007-02-06T06:29:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/a-quiet-purchase</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I bought something that I know I should have bought a long time ago. In fact, I should have bought it at the same time that I bought my <a href="http://www.hisdigital.com/html/product_ov.php?id=217" title="HIS x1900xtx" target="_blank">video card</a>.  In case you didn&rsquo;t know, the stock fan that comes with this video card is by far the noisiest <strong>ever</strong>. It&rsquo;s the loudest in their line of video cards, and I think it might even be the loudest across all cards.  I admit that I didn&rsquo;t know that it was going to be that noisy when I first bought the card, and I was disappointed to find that it made all my other efforts to make a quiet case pointless :( Without the video card, it was hard to tell if the PC was on! With the card, it sounded like a jet engine waiting to take off.</p>

<p>The solution: <a href="http://www.zalman.co.kr/eng/product/view.asp?idx=192&code=013" title="Zalman VF900-cu" target="_blank">Zalman VF900-cu</a>.</p>

<p>When I installed it last night I was beyond happy. The quiet <a href="http://www.scythe-usa.com/product/cpu/001/index.html" title="Ninja Scythe" target="_blank">HSF</a>, quiet <a href="http://www.antec.com/us/productDetails.php?ProdID=81800" title="Antec P180" target="_blank">case</a>, and the quiet <a href="http://www.nexustek.nl/120mmcasefan.htm" title="Nexus 120mm case fan" target="_blank">case fans</a> were in blissful silence alongside this masterpiece. My case was silent again! This piece of kit is fantastic. Go get one if you need peace :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
