<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Linux | OJ's rants]]></title>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-26T16:47:20+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://buffered.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OJ Reeves]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Server Refresh]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/server-refresh/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-16T07:24:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/server-refresh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the weekend I revamped the webserver. Over the last month or two I've been bummed about the amount of overhead in maintaining a <a href="Gentoo" title="http://www.gentoo.org/">Gentoo</a> install as my webserver. Now before any of you Gentoo zealots have a whinge, let me explain.</p>

<p>Yes, <a href="Portage" title="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portage_(software)">Portage</a> is cool. It's quick, it builds stuff from source, etc. While that power is great, it's a pain in the butt at the same time. Especially when you're running on a <a href="VPS" title="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_private_server">VPS</a>. I am tired of the underlying bits and pieces changing constantly and me having to muck around with masking and unmasking packages just to get things to update and play nicely together.</p>

<p>I made the decision to switch to <a href="Debian" title="http://www.debian.org/">Debian</a> and I am happy I did it. I don't think the time I'll have to spend maintaining the server will be as high as before. This is all about productivity and as far as I'm concerned this is going to reduce my workload. Given that my software installs don't change once I've got the server up and running, I shouldn't have to spend that amount of time keeping things running.</p>

<p>As always, there's a risk of teething problems when you do a full reinstall. So if anyone out there is having issues then please <a href="Contact me" title="/contact-me/">let me know</a>. Cheers! :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Admin is an Idiot]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/the-admin-is-an-idiot/"/>
    <updated>2008-12-27T12:51:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/the-admin-is-an-idiot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yes, and that admin is me!</p>

<p>I usually do a fairly decent job of keeping the server patched, up to date, and clean. Over the Xmas period where I wasn't really looking at anything online, something went wrong.</p>

<p>I logged on this morning only to find that the server wasn't responding. I could connect via SSH, but nothing was being served via HTTP. So I tried to reboot <a href="http://litespeedtech.com/" title="LiteSpeed technologies">LiteSpeed</a> to see if that would resolve it (as you do ;) ). The service stopped, but failed to restart!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I was a bit concerned when this happened. So I thought I'd check to see if there were any server updates (in case there was a known issue preventing the server from working). I found that there had been an update, so I jumped to my first conclusion and assumed that this was broken. I attempted to download the new version onto my <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_private_server" title="Virtual Private Server">VPS</a>, but it failed. The error message said that it couldn't download the file because I was out of disk space!</p>

<p>A quick run of <a href="http://www.computerhope.com/unix/udf.htm" title="Linux 'df' command">df</a> told me that the error message was indeed correct. 19GB out of 19GB was used. Crap.</p>

<p>I then jumped to my second conclusion and immediately blamed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portage_(software)" title="Portage">portage</a> for downloading too much stuff that it didn't need. After a quick <a href="http://linuxlore.blogspot.com/2007/04/howto-cleanup-gentoo-portage-distfiles.html" title="Clean up Gentoo Portage Distfiles">eclean</a> I was presented with a huge saving of 350MB. Crap.</p>

<p>I then had to fall back on <a href="http://www.computerhope.com/unix/udu.htm" title="Linux 'du' command">du</a> (<em>du -h --max-depth=1</em> to be exact) to try and narrow down the folder(s) which were chewing up disk space.</p>

<p>To cut a long story short, there were two culprits. The first was the linux source folder. I had 15 copies of the Gentoo source in there, and freed up 4.7GB by deleting 13 of them. The second was, much to my shame and dismay, the web server log files folder. Oh woe is me.</p>

<p>Schoolboy error. I scrapped all the unnecessary logs and freed up yet another 5.6GB. Amazingly, everything has started behaving itself again! Who'd have thought.</p>

<p>So the server is now back online. Normality has been restored. I also have more proof that I'm an idiot.</p>

<p>That is all :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reactivate? AGAIN!?]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/reactivate-again/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-27T12:29:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/reactivate-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is just a quick post to say how much Microsoft and their draconian OS licensing mechanism are pissing me off right now.</p>

<p>Last week my computer stopped booting. I didn't get around to looking at it until a few days ago because I had visitors over from the UK. Not just that, it is Christmas, and the last thing you want to be doing on your Christmas break is to be fixing computers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I spent an hour or two playing with bits and pieces to try and determine the error. The problem was that the third <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DIMM" title="DIMM">DIMM</a> slot on <a href="http://us.dfi.com.tw/Product/xx_product_spec_details_r_us.jsp?PRODUCT_ID=4556&CATEGORY_TYPE=LP%20UT&SITE=NA" title="DFI Lanparty CFX3200-DR">my motherboard</a> (which, incidentally, has been a bit of a nightmare since I bought it) is dodgey. I removed a 512MB RAM stick from the offending slot over to slot two and the machine started to come alive again. I was pretty happy about this, despite the reduction in RAM speed due to the configuration, since I didn't need to buy anything to make it work again!</p>

<p>So I left the machine for a couple of days again as I was happy with what I achieved. But today, because the study was in a bit of a state due to the bits of computers, manuals, and various other things I'd strewn around the room while investigating, I thought I'd finalise everything and tidy up.</p>

<p>Since my computer case was open, I thought I'd do a bit of housekeeping. I wasn't really happy with the way it was laid out inside so I thought I'd tidy that up a bit first. I removed <a href="http://www.linksys.com/servlet/Satellite?c=L_Product_C2&childpagename=US%2FLayout&cid=1150490054358&pagename=Linksys%2FCommon%2FVisitorWrapper" title="Linksys WMP54G">my WLAN card</a> because it was flaky at best in 64-bit, and I'd had enough of the lag spikes (time to go back to cabled LAN). I moved <a href="http://www.hisdigital.com/html/product_ov.php?id=217" title="HIS Radeon x1900xtx">my video card</a> to a different slot to create a bit more space between it and <a href="http://www.scythe-usa.com/product/cpu/006/scnj1000p.html" title="Ninja Scythe">my HSF</a> (which is awesome, and does a great job even if it is a behemoth!). I also adjusted the fans a bit, cleaned up a lot of the dust, and moved a few of the cables around to improve air-flow.</p>

<p>So with all that done, I fired up the machine.</p>

<p>.. and got nothing. <strong>Shit</strong>.</p>

<p>The investigation started again. I thought that I'd go right for the previous culprit and rip out the RAM stick that I'd moved to see if that would resolve the problem. Thankfully, it did. So right now I'm running on 1/2GB RAM, not ideal to say the least but the machine is booting which is a lot better than it not.</p>

<p>The machine booted, and up came windows. It was at this point that I remember it telling me that a few days back it wanted me to reactivate Windows because of a <em>substantial change in hardware</em>. Of course, I ignored this stupid box because at the time I hadn't changed <strong>anything</strong>. I'd <em>moved a RAM stick</em>!</p>

<p>But today, it greeted me again. This time the message was different. In essense, my 3-day "window" of reactivation had expired, and I was being forced to reactivate it now. And I do mean <strong>now</strong>. Now as in right now before I was allowed to log on. Oh, but there's a problem here you see, because prior to logging on, there's no network connection. So when you try and activate Windows before logging on, it can't activate over the Interweb because it can't get to it. Of course, the activation fails. But does it let me log in? No. What does it do? I ties itself into an infinite loop of ...<ol><li>Try to log in.</li><li>Fail because it's not activated.</li><li>Try to activate.</li><li>Fail to activate because it's not logged in and hence can't connect.</li><li>Goto step 1.</li></ol>Not happy. Not happy at all. Not only had I <strong>not</strong> changed any hardware in the system (all I'd done is move it around, and remove a WLAN card) to force the reactivation, I am now stuck with a machine that won't let me log in. Nice eh?</p>

<p>Here's a nice little side-note for the Linux fanboys :) (yes, you know who you are). For yonks, a slight modification in anything to do with the video hardware in my machine would result in my linux graphics setup shitting itself. I'd then have to spend a chunk of the day trying to get it to work again with my dual-screen setup. But not this time. I'd mucked around with everything inside the machine, and what happened when I booted Linux??</p>

<p>Wait for it... WAIT FOR IT!</p>

<p>Nothing. It booted as if nothing had changed. Video settings were the same. Dual-screen worked. I sat here a little stunned for a while and I was brought back from my daze by the little blinking icon in the system tray telling me that I had updates to download. The network had connected, and everything was sweet.</p>

<p>See that Microsoft? Right there. <strong>That</strong> is what <em>should</em> happen. Nothing more, nothing less. When I reboot after a hardware change, I expect you to continue as if nothing had happened. I expect the network to connect without me dicking with it. I expect a nice little "Hello OJ, you legend, how else can I make your life easy today?"</p>

<p>So hats off to you <a href="http://www.linuxmint.com/" title="LinuxMint">LinuxMint</a>. You made my day! Now, if only you hadn't borked my Firefox install :) Time to update you to the last version me thinks, and give you a bit of the love and attention that you deserve.</p>

<p>As a final note, it looks like I'm going to have to buy some new RAM, and while I'm there I'm going to ditch this UK keyboard as it has been driving me nuts for the last year and half. Time to get back to the Aussie (some might say US) layout.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PCs for the Family]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/pcs-for-the-family/"/>
    <updated>2006-11-09T07:59:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/pcs-for-the-family</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I know for sure that many of the geeks out there on the World Wide Wibbly have the "fun" task of sorting out every possible computer issue for any/all of their family and friends in the cases where they're not geeks themselves. I am one such geek, and I'll be honest and say that I do not mind helping out. It's actually a bit of fun! I starting pondering thoughts on this topic when I stumbled across Roy's <a href="http://weblogs.asp.net/rosherove/archive/posts/MomPC-_2D00_-Creating-a-parent-safe-PC.aspx" title="ISerializable - Roy Osherove's Blog : MomPC - Creating a parent safe PC" target="_blank">MomPC</a> blog post a week or two ago. I read the post with interest and think that it's quite a handy little reference for those people looking to achieve the same thing.</p>

<p>By the same token, I think there are some gaps in what was said. I also think that there's a fundamental flaw in the assumption that Windows XP has to be used as the operating system. I'll get onto that point a bit more in a moment, but for now I'd like to comment on a few other options that Roy hasn't covered.</p>

<p><strong><u>Firewall</u></strong></p>

<p>The main reasons for having a software firewall on Windows is to prevent nasty trojans from getting <em>out</em> to do their thing, and to prevent other trojans and script kiddies (<em>skiddies</em>) from getting <em>in</em>. Windows Defender is indeed one option, but it's not the only one. <a href="http://www.webmasterfree.com/tpfw.html" title="Tiny Firewall" target="_blank">Tiny Firewall</a> is a nice option (though it looks like it might not be supported any more!) which is free for home use, and there's always <a href="http://www.zonelabs.com/store/content/company/products/znalm/freeDownload.jsp?dc=12bms&ctry=GB&lang=en" title="Zone Labs ZoneAlarm" target="_blank">ZoneAlarm</a> which is also free for home use. These two do a good enough job as well. The latter has improved somewhat now that it no longer "phones home" while protecting you :)</p>

<p><strong><u>Antivirus</u></strong></p>

<p>I've never been a huge advocate of AVG, so I don't agree with Roy on this point. Instead I have found that both the 32 and 64-bit versions of <a href="http://www.avast.com/" title="Avast" target="_blank">Avast</a> do a <em>very</em> good job of keeping the baddies at bay. I've been using this for well over a year now at home, and I have nothing but good things to say about it. People's experiences do vary though, so take my comments with a grain of salt. If you're looking for a freebie that's good, then Avast is a winner.</p>

<p><strong><u>Email</u></strong></p>

<p>I'd strongly recommend the use of <a href="http://www.mozilla.com/thunderbird/" title="Mozilla Thunderbird" target="_blank">Thunderbird</a> for all email-based stuff. This removes the need for having Outlook and/or Outlook Express installed at all. It's got a built-in news reader and RSS feed reader, and is basically a fabulous comms application - better yet it's a freebie!</p>

<p><strong><u>Office Applications</u></strong></p>

<p>For most home users, I personally feel that buying a licenced copy of Microsoft Office is overkill. People write a letter here and there, they might open a few word docs that are downloaded off the web, or want to open up some crappy powerpoint presentation with the latest "fluffy bunnies in tu-tus wishing you wealth, happiness and friendship for the rest of your days" accompanied with some cheezy music and awful text animations.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, <a href="http://www.openoffice.org/" title="OpenOffice" target="_blank">OpenOffice</a> is more than sufficient for these purposes. Again, it's free software, it has fairly regular releases (given that it's a rather large application) and it's cross-platform too. I can't see the need to go for another office application which costs a fortune when 9 time out of 10 this will suffice.</p>

<p>Of course, there are cases where people need more than just a standard word processor. OpenOffice has its quirks and pitfalls, and if you're looking to go for a package with a lot of functionality then MS Office might just be on the cards for you.</p>

<p><strong><u>Browser</u></strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.getfirefox.com/" title="FireFox" target="_blank">FireFox</a>. 'Nuff said.</p>

<p><strong><u>The Key Point - What Operating System?</u></strong></p>

<p>As I stated at the start of this post, I'm not really sure why Windows XP has to be the default installation for a family PC. The big thing that most people will focus on here is usability, followed closely by the range of software and support for things such as scanners, digital cameras and MP3 players - which you can't argue with to a point.</p>

<p>In Roy's case, I think Windows XP is unnecessary. I think a default installation of Ubuntu with all the required software set up would be more than enough for the default family PC. It'd be a lot easier to secure, wouldn't require constant maintenance and reinstalling every few months like Windows does, and doesn't cost a bean. Ubuntu with FireFox, Thunderbird, OpenOffice and perhaps a few games (Solitaire, Mahjongg, etc) would keep the average non-geek family member amused for hours, and would probably cover most, if not all, of the things that the users want to do. The set up of a software firewall wouldn't be so much of an issue since there's very little (to no) malware that runs on Linux, hence it's probably not needed. You don't <em>need</em> to run antivirus software (though I still think you should) on Linux as 99.99999% of viruses are targetted at the Windows platform. Finally, auto-updates are on by default which means the OS keeps itself up to date just like the Auto-update feature of Windows.</p>

<p>Bring on Ubuntu installs for the family I say! There's no need to give yourself the extra workload of maintaining a family Windows machine when it doesn't have to have Windows running on it. Do yourself, and your family a favour - get yourself a Linus distro, and just see how much longer it lasts before you have to blast it away and reinstall from scratch.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HOWTO: Getting ATi Drivers Working in Ubuntu]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/howto-getting-ati-drivers-working-in-ubuntu/"/>
    <updated>2006-10-25T22:07:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/howto-getting-ati-drivers-working-in-ubuntu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I've already mentioned, I've started dabbling in the joys of Linux by installing Ubuntu (<a href="http://www.ubuntu.com/support/faq#head-3df1e0e29bc1a807664ce156fb9fe6f09c35bfdd" title="Ubuntu FAQ" target="_blank">Dapper Drake</a>). This was partly joyous and partly painful - but mostly joyous :) While going through some of the less enjoyable moments I spent a fair bit of time trawling forums and hanging in IRC channels (#ubuntu-au on irc.freenode.net to be exact, check out <a href="http://ubuntu.com.au/welcome/" title="Ubuntu Australian Team" target="_blank">here</a> and <a href="http://www.matthewv.id.au/ubuntu-au/" title="Ubuntu Australian Team" target="_blank">here</a>) trying to find the information I needed to get things going.</p>

<p>The most recent issue that I have since solved is that of getting drivers working with my ATi Radeon X1900-XTX, and it was the pain of this set up that inspired me to write this post - and in fact, what will look to be a long stream of posts. After the quality of feedback and help, and the time investment by some of the guys in #ubuntu-au (thanks lads! Especially <em>DarkMageZ</em> and <em>siccness</em>), I thought that I want to help share this information to aid in getting other people up to speed to. In fact, I've decided to start a whole new category of blog posts - HOWTOs! You can consider this the first :) I won't just be doing HOWTOs on things that I experience with Linux, but I'll aim to cover code examples, bits and pieces to do with Windows, and whatever else takes my fancy. Information should be shared, so feel free to let me know if anything that you would like me to share, and I'll do my best to cover it.</p>

<p>So, on with the juicy bits. The default installation of Ubunutu worked fine with the vesa driver which allowed Xorg to fire up without any issues, but of course, I wasn't happy to suffer for second best while having a fairly beefy video card. The goal was to get the ATi drivers working in both 2D and 3D.</p>

<p>The first mistake that I made was to approach the issue in the same way that I would approach it as a Windows user - that is, go to the ATi driver website and download the latest driver. This turned out to be a bit of a mistake, but I'll go through the process I took anyway just FYI :) I downloaded the driver from the <a href="http://www.ati.com/online/customercareportal/linux.html" title="Linux ATi Drivers" target="_blank">ATi Linux driver page</a> and read the instructions that came with it. Seemed fairly simple, so I did as I was told and waited for the magic to happen.</p>

<p>The first thing that I failed to notice was that the install notes stated that the driver had only been tested with Red Hat Linux. Now I don't know if there is that much of a difference between that and Ubuntu, but given that certain things refused to work I'm <em>guessing</em> they are. After performing the installation, I restarted Xorg (which, FYI, can be done using the shortcut <strong>CTRL+ALT+BACKSPACE</strong>) and I was knocked off my chair by the clarity of what I was seeing. It was magic :) But to my dismay, things were not all good under the hood. It turned out that even though 2D was clearly working, the 3D part (and with it OpenGL functionality) was nowhere to be seen. This is what got me started with the forum trawling and the IRC rants. I learned very quickly that downloading the driver from the ATi site was a bad move, and that I should have instead used the <strong>apt-get</strong> functionality to get the drivers set up.</p>

<p>At this point I went through the process of uninstalling the drivers that I had downloaded, and got my machine back to a point where I could try and install the new ones. The <em>vesa</em> driver fuzzyness returned and I was ready to rock with the instructions I was given. I downloaded and installed the correct drivers using the correct utility and did exactly what I was told to do, only to find that this refused to work as well. The driver install was apparently successful, but I still had the VESA fuzzyness indicating that the driver was not loading properly. I read around some more, and chatted some more, and determined that I needed to modify my <strong>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</strong> file to set the default video driver to <strong>fglrx</strong> (not VESA), so that's what I did!</p>

<p>Restarting Xorg resulted in my world crumbling (well, not quite ;)). My screen was blank. I had no UI, I had no idea what was on screen, so I ended up having to boot back in using recovery mode and modifying the file so that it was set back to VESA. It was about this time I was getting pretty narked as I'd been messing with quite a few things for a few hours and my patience was wearing thin.  It was 11:45pm when I thanked my Aussie Ubuntu colleagues for their help and made the move to shut down, as I was going to continue tackling the problem the next day. While shutting down, I was just having a last flick through the tabs I had open in FireFox when I noticed a comment at the bottom of a forum thread. This turned out to be the magic missile!</p>

<p>There are a stack of modules that you can specify to load in Xorg, and apparently there's issues with the ATi driver when two of the many are loaded at the same time. The suggestion was to comment out the culprit (which was called <strong>extmod</strong> I believe) which was clashing with the one you needed (which was called <strong>dri</strong>, I think :)). After making this change, I restarted Xorg and all was clear and beautiful! And for the first time ever on this new installation both <strong>fglrxinfo</strong> and <strong>glxgears</strong> behaved the way they should. 2D and 3D was up and running! Mission accomplished.  So, now that my story is told, please find listed below the steps that I had to take to get the ATi drivers installed on Ubuntu AMD64 Dapper Drake. I hope you find them useful.</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install xorg-driver-fglrx fglrx-control
sudo aticonfig --initial

take a backup copy of /etc/X11/xorg.conf
edit /etc/X11/xorg.conf using your favourite text editor:
- change the Driver option from "vesa" to "fglrx"
- comment out the line that says : Load "extmod"

restart xorg (CTRL+ALT+BACKSPACE)
</code></pre>

<p>Good luck all! Hopefully next up will be my success story with my wireless network card.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
