<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: WTF | OJ's rants]]></title>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/categories/wtf/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-19T18:21:15+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://buffered.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OJ Reeves]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Expert at 23]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/an-expert-at-23/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-27T20:59:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/an-expert-at-23</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was about to head to bed when I stumbled across a poorly-titled <a href="http://www.news.com.au/business/the-best-places-to-look-for-work-in-2012/story-e6frfm1i-1226255099978" title="The best places to look for work in 2012">article on news.com.au</a>. At first I thought it was going to cover off the best locations around Australia, or perhaps the world, for finding work in a variety of industries. It turned out to be a failed attempt at highlighting the key growth industry areas for jobs in Australia.</p>

<p>It began like this:</p>

<blockquote><p>JOBS demanded across several booming sectors will be the best place to find work this year.</p></blockquote>

<p>Despite the appalling structure and lack of coherence of the opening paragraph I pushed on through the rest of the article, hoping to find some interesting or useful information. Most of content would be fairly obvious to almost every Australian. The bits that could be considered interesting were old news, and nothing in the article made me feel that reading it was a good use of time.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Then I got to the end and found this:</p>

<blockquote><p>For IT expert <em>Joe Public</em>, 23, right, the telecommunications and digital industry holds the promise of future growth. <em>Joe</em> studied IT at the University of Technology before completing a one-year placement at Macquarie Telecom.</p>

<p>"The industry is enormous and there's plenty of variations and specialisations that you can pursue," he says.</p>

<p><em>Joe</em> now sets up servers and IT networks for various clients' business applications.</p>

<p>Asked where he would like to be in five years' time, he says: "What I like is that I can go into a lot of different directions from where I am."</p></blockquote>

<p>I tried to completely ignore the blatant mistakes but couldn't. Despite the use of the word "right" in the first sentence there was no picture of the interviewee to be found. There's a mention of "the University of Technology" but a failure to mention which one. If this person finished a degree, taking a minimum of 3 years to complete, that would mean that his one year placement finished at the ripe old age of 22 if we assume he started university at 18. This is best case. Working for another year, bringing him to 23 years old, caps his experience at 2 years maximum -- not much for someone considered to be an <em>I.T. expert</em>, in the "digital industry" no less!</p>

<p>{% pullquote %}
I've been working professionally as a software developer/engineer/whatever since 1999. During this time I've spent a great deal of time learning, growing, failing, constantly trying to improve, and earning scars along the way. I've been fortunate enough to experience a huge number of different domains within software and have managed to land jobs in other countries than the one that I live in. Now that I am starting my 14th year in the industry I think I might be able to say that I'm no longer a junior. {" At 23 years old I barely knew my object-oriented earhole from my procedural arsehole"}, let alone have the gall to call myself an expert or allow someone else to refer to me as one. Doing otherwise would be a lie. To grossly over-generalise: <em>nobody at the age of 23 can be called an I.T. expert</em>. Add at least ten years before you're no longer wet behind the ears.
{% endpullquote %}</p>

<p><a href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2012/01/senior-lead-expert.jpg" rel="lightbox"><img title="Senior Lead Expert" src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2012/01/senior-lead-expert.jpg" width="200" style="float:right;margin-left:5px;margin-bottom:5px" /></a>Even the people that I know and respect, who I consider to be amongst the best, would not think of themselves as experts in their field by that age. To think that is to be overly arrogant. To allow a newspaper to state it on your behalf is stupid and I would consider it more damaging to your reputation than anything else. Don't attempt to make yourself sound like more than you are, as more often than not you tend to come off looking like a fool (see the "Senior Lead Expert" to the right for another example).</p>

<p>Another issue I have with this article, and others that have this focus, is that they imply that these industry sectors are the ones to go for if you're looking for a job <em>regardless of whether you're interested in the field or not</em>.</p>

<p>I love what I do. I enjoy most of the work that I am asked to undertake, and more often than not enjoy working with the people in the teams I get to work in. I don't dread getting out of bed and going to work. I look forward to the challenges, and I aim to produce quality stuff where possible while bettering myself in the process. To me, this is way more than a job. It's part of me and I love it.</p>

<p>If you don't love it, don't do it. Don't do it for the money. It's not worth it, for you or for the people you'll work with. If you love it, and you're interested, then the industry will welcome you with open arms. If all you've ever wanted to be is a puppeteer, then go do that instead.</p>

<p><strong>News.com.au</strong> have done themselves, and Joe Public, a disservice with this article. It's poorly written, lacks anything newsworthy, implies that the subject is claiming to be something he is not, and guides people to a number of industries for the wrong reasons.</p>

<p>If you want to read news which is meaningful, well-written, edited and at least researched to a semi-decent level, then try the <a href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/" title="ABC News">ABC</a> instead.</p>

<h3>NOTE</h3>

<p>This article is not targeting <em>Joe Public</em>, it is instead attacking the way that the newspaper has portrayed him.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go With Your Instinct]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/go-with-your-instinct/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-25T16:31:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/go-with-your-instinct</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2011/02/double-facepalm.jpg" rel="lightbox"><img src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2011/02/double-facepalm.jpg" width="150" style="float:left;margin-right:5px;margin-bottom:5px;" /></a>At an early age I realised that it's not always a bad thing to go with your first instinct. I won't go into the reasons here, nor the way I came to that conclusion. What I will say is that I wish I'd listened to my inner-8-year-old-self when I started down the thread of emails and Tweets you're about to read.</p>

<p>Suffice is to say that I have learned my lesson!</p>

<p>The thread speaks for itself. Enjoy :)</p>

<!--more-->






<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Wednesday 23 Feb 2011 4.15 PM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br />
Program has crashing on random times. Everything tried is not fix it.<br />
PLEASE THIS IS URGENT ONE NOW. <br />
All detail attached.<br />
I ahve manager breathing down neck have two customer angry.<br />
I look everywhere your blog is kindest help please thank.<br />
Reward in heaven.<br />
Al Soong<br />
<img src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2011/02/attachment.png"/><br/>
</blockquote>


<hr />


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1234939088/Profile_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/TheColonial/status/40295102056239104">TheColonial</a></h2>
<p>Third email like this in as many days. Perhaps if "reward in heaven" wasn't written I may have helped. <a href="http://twitpic.com/42t2sj">http://twitpic.com/42t2sj</a></p>
</div>


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1234939088/Profile_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/TheColonial/status/40296042956066816">TheColonial</a></h2>
<p>Shame. All that was in the doc was a very blurry and hard to read image with a stack trace that I can't read.</p>
</div>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Wednesday 23 Feb 2011 4.24 PM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br /> 
Sorry to hear of your issues. The image that you have sent me is extremely poor quality and I'm unable to read it. <br />
Please send a screenshot as a PNG/JPG or just copy and paste the text into an email. Don't use word.<br />
<br />
OJ<br />
<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Wednesday 23 Feb 2011 4.17 PM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br />
happen AGAIN!<br />
<br />

> Program has crashing on random times. Everything tried is not fix it.<br />
> PLEASE THIS IS URGENT ONE NOW. <br />
> All detail attached.<br />
> I ahve manager breathing down neck have two customer angry.<br />
> I look everywhere your blog is kindest help please thank.<br />
> Reward in heaven.<br />
> Al Soong <br />

<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1234939088/Profile_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/TheColonial/status/40297392909582336">TheColonial</a></h2>
<p>*sigh* some people have no idea how to get help <a href="http://twitpic.com/42t54u">http://twitpic.com/42t54u</a></p>
</div>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Wednesday 23 Feb 2011 4.30 PM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br />
Uninstalling word now. what next?<br />
<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1234939088/Profile_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/TheColonial/status/40299003639758848">TheColonial</a></h2>
<p>Christ on a Bike, this guy is writing code?! #fail <a href="http://twitpic.com/42t6s1">http://twitpic.com/42t6s1</a></p>
</div>


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1060266034/twitter_avatar_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/rbanks54/status/40304384470425600">rbanks54</a></h2>
<p>ROFLMAO!!! That's priceless. The next step is to tell him to pack his pc in a box because he's not qualified to use it</p>
</div>


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1234939088/Profile_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/TheColonial/status/40347229483040768">TheColonial</a></h2>
<p>@rbanks54 and this dude is apparently a developer! Fark :-)</p>
</div>


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a0.twimg.com/profile_images/1187162790/profilepic-2010-12-10_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/DamonOehlman/status/40303061285076992">DamonOehlman</a></h2>
<p>@TheColonial OK, that is awesomely funny. Admittedly you did tell him not to use word :)</p>
</div>


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1234939088/Profile_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/TheColonial/status/40304430628868096">TheColonial</a></h2>
<p>@DamonOehlman if someone told you to not use your oven to make ice cream would your rip the oven out of the wall? :-D</p>
</div>


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a1.twimg.com/profile_images/82675101/n710576649_899427_1819_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/DamianM/status/40300422925254657">DamianM</a></h2>
<p>@TheColonial HAHAHA That's awesome! Maybe you tell him he needs to close his windows, his screen will go blank and he'll stop bothering you</p>
</div>


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1234939088/Profile_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/TheColonial/status/40304606894489600">TheColonial</a></h2>
<p>@DamianM yeah :-) should have gone with my first impulse and ignored him.</p>
</div>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Wednesday 23 Feb 2011 4.34 PM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br />
Don't uninstall word. I'm asking you to send me the stack trace in a form that I can read!<br />
<br />
Just paste the text of the error into an email directly<br />
<br />
OJ<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Wednesday 23 Feb 2011 9.30 PM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br />
Thank you. You are right! Even uninstall word cannot fix of the site.<br />
My normal word is the linux. I cannot find to send you the stack trace in a form. What form is it? <br />
<br />
The citrix not allow cuts and paste. Do you FAX or SKYPE? I read you message.<br />
<br />
This to:<br />
<pre>
Program Location:
   at Microsoft.SqlServer.Management.DataTools.Interop.IDTDocTool.Save(Object dsRef, String path, Boolean okToOverwrite)
   at Microsoft.SqlServer.Management.UI.VSIntegration.Editors.VsDataDesignerNode.Save(VSSAVEFLAGS dwSave, String strSilentSaveAsName, IVsUIShell pIVsUIShell, IntPtr punkDocDataIntPtr, String& strMkDocumentNew, Int32& pfCanceled)
</pre>
<br />
HURRY PLEASE<br />
<br />
Reward in heaven.<br />
Al Soong<br />
<br />
***************************************************************************************************<br />
***Blessed be the Lord who has given rest to his people Israel, according to all that he***<br/>
***promised. Not one word has failed of all his good promise, which he spoke by Moses his***<br />
***servant.                                                                                 ***<br />
***************************************************************************************************<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Wednesday 23 Feb 2011 10.56 PM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br />
Alwyn,<br />
<br />
Make sure you read what I am saying, and read it properly. I never once told you to uninstall Word, I just told you not to use it to send me the details of your issue.<br />
<br />
Citrix shouldn't stop you from copying and pasting, but if it does, take a screenshot like you did before and open "Paint". you should find it in the "accessories menu". when you've opened paint, paste the screenshot in there, and save the image as a jpg, png or bmp. Then attach that to an email and send it to me.<br />
<br />
Sorry, but I am not giving out fax or skype details. Trust me, you're getting way more out of this than you deserve.<br />
<br />
OJ<br />
<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Thursday 24 Feb 2011 7.30 AM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br />
HURRY PLEASE. WE GO LIVE IN 20 MINUTES.<br />
Maybe you look at site yourself and see error please. it is here <a href='http://127.0.0.1:8081/mailout/'>http://127.0.0.1:8081/mailout/</a><br />
Click the MAILOUT button then CHURCH NEWS. Wait for OUTLOOK LOADING stop the blink. Type the MESSAGE for the people and click the GO SEND.<br />
<br />
you to can getting more out of this than you deserve. My company is biggest oil 2nd company in singapore. please to send CV and we keep you remember if new opening. I have email of you will KEEP.<br />
<br />
In heaven please the angels felate you.<br />
Al Soong<br />
<br />
12:1 Therefore, since we are surrounded by so great a cloud of witnesses, let us also lay aside every weight, and sin which clings so closely, and let us run with endurance the race that is set before us, 2 looking to Jesus, the founder and perfecter of our faith, who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross, despising the shame, and is seated at the right hand of the throne of God.<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Thursday 24 Feb 2011 8.29 AM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> fix my viewstate<br />
<br />
Is a windows 32 64
<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Thursday 24 Feb 2011 10.15 AM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> Lingli Farhat<br />
<strong>Cc:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> Re: UPDATE PLEASE<br />
<br />
10 MORE MINUTES and ALL fixed then good friend OJ fixing. Say HI! boardroom.<br />
<br />

> subject: UPDATE PLEASE<br />
> Thursday, 24 February, 2011 12:11 AM<br />
> From: Lingli Farhat<br />
> To: alwyn soong<br />
> AN UPDATE PLEASE ALWYN.<br />
><br />
> WE ARE WAITING FOR YOUR GRACIOUS PRESENCE IN THE BOARD ROOM AND WISH TO HEAR ONLY HAPPY NEWS.<br />
><br />
> OUR PATIENCE IS CERTAINLY TESTED THIS HOUR.<br />
><hr/>
> No one has ever seen God; if we love one another, God abides in us and his love is perfected in us.<br />
><hr/>
> Free POP3 Email from www.gawab.com<br />
> Sign up NOW and get your account @gawab.com!!<br />

</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Lingli Farhat<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Thursday 24 Feb 2011 10.49 AM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Cc:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> RE: re: UPDATE PLEASE<br />
 <br />
TIME IS MOST CERTAINLY "UP" ALWYN.<br />
<br />
I HAVE LOOKED AGAIN AND THE EXPLORER IS STILL EMPTY  <a href='http://127.0.0.1:8081/mailout/'>http://127.0.0.1:8081/mailout/</a><br />
<br />
I WILL SEE YOU AND YOUR "OJ" FRIEND IN MY OFFICE BEFORE TODAY IS "UP" <br />
<br />
FATHER LINGLI FARHAT<br />
<br />
OFFICE OF THE MINISTER<br />
<hr/>
The thoughts of the wicked are an abomination to the Lord, but gracious words are pure.<br />
<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Thursday 24 Feb 2011 11.01 AM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Cc:</strong> Lingli Farhat<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> RE: re: UPDATE PLEASE<br />
 <br />
OJ good frien please in dark hour. I HAVE THE VIEWSTATE! I HAVE IT! THIS IS HERE<br />
 <br />
Took all day to copy out<br />
 <br />
QSBqb2tlJ3Mgbm90IGEgam9rZSB1bnRpbCBpdCBnb2VzICp0b28qIGZhci4NCkxvdHMgb2YgbG92<br />
ZQ0KTGVvbg0Kd2l0aCBoZWxwIGZyb20gUmh5cyBhbmQgSm9lbC4NCkFsc28gQkNDJ2QgLS0gSm9z<br />
ZXBoLg==<br />
<br />
If you read it for me I get OUT from hair. Expertschange sayt BASE64????? <br />
 <br />
Reward in heaven<br />
Al Soong<br />
CHIEF ENGINEER<br />
 <br />
************************************************************************************************************<br />
***22 But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness,   ***<br/>
***23 gentleness, self-control; against such things there is no law.                                    ***<br />
<br />
************************************************************************************************************<br />
<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<p>The garbled text above, when <a href="http://www.motobit.com/util/base64-decoder-encoder.asp">base 64 decoded</a> reads:</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
A joke's not a joke until it goes *too* far.
Lots of love
Leon
with help from Rhys and Joel.
Also BCC'd -- Joseph.
</pre>
</blockquote>


<hr />


<div class="tweet"><img src="http://a2.twimg.com/profile_images/1234939088/Profile_normal.jpg"/><h2><a href="http://twitter.com/#!/TheColonial/status/40577362336677889">TheColonial</a></h2>
<p>I've just been absolutely owned by some soon to be ex-friends :) Great prank.. you utter, utter bastards :)</p>
</div>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Thursday 24 Feb 2011 11.11 AM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> ERLANG<br />
<br />
Now i learn erlang.<br />
 <br />
You teach me please.<br />
 <br />
What first? <br />
<br />
</blockquote>


<hr />


<blockquote>
<strong>From:</strong> OJ<br />
<strong>Date:</strong> Thursday 24 Feb 2011 11.56 AM<br />
<strong>To:</strong> Alwyn Soong<br />
<strong>Subject:</strong> RE: ERLANG<br />
<br />
sure.. start with this:<br />
{% codeblock lang:erlang %}
self() ! bullet.
{% endcodeblock %}

</blockquote>


<hr />


<p><a href="http://secretgeek.net/">Leon</a>, <a href="http://i-think22.net/">Rhys</a>, <a href="http://callvirt.net/">Joel</a> and to a point <a href="http://jcooney.net/">Joseph</a>: you've started a war!</p>

<p>Well played :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ASP.NET MVC 2, Random Sign-offs and TempData Loss]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/asp-net-mvc-2-random-sign-offs-and-tempdata-loss/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-06T08:39:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/asp-net-mvc-2-random-sign-offs-and-tempdata-loss</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a title="MVC" href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2010/10/mvc.png" rel="lightbox[contentadvisor]"><img style="margin-left: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px; float: right;" src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2010/10/mvc.png" alt="MVC" width="150" /></a>In the last few days I've been working on resolving issues in a production system which runs on <a title="What is ASP.NET MVC" href="http://www.asp.net/mvc/whatisaspmvc">ASP.NET MVC 2</a>. Most of the issues were actually really easy to resolve and the team of developers were able to fix them and deploy to production without too many problems.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, as always, there was one problem in particular that had us scratching our heads and was causing some of us to lose sleep. All over the Internet there were posts of people describing similar symptoms yet none of them revealed a solid answer.</p>

<p>The purpose of this post is to document the issue and the resolution in it's entirety. It's in story form rather than reference form because that's how I felt like writing it :)</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Issue</h2>

<p>First of all, the percentage of users that were experiencing this problem was relatively low, less than 1 in every 400. This is low enough to indicate that we were going to have one hell of a time finding the issue.</p>

<p>So what was the issue?</p>

<p>The <strong>entry-point</strong> to the site was the <strong>sign-in</strong> page. This is the first page that the user sees. In short, users would sign in to the site and be presented with the landing page in the authenticated area of the site. As soon as they attempted to click on <em>any</em> link inside the authenticated area they were <strong>immediately sent back to the sign-in page</strong>.</p>

<h2>The Investigation</h2>

<p>After adding some more logging functionality to the application and talking to one of our users, we were able to see some really odd behaviour. The user would sign-in, again they were presented with their landing page. Before the user clicked on anything else, we could see that the system had recorded that the browser had <strong>already invoked the sign-off functionality</strong>.</p>

<p>Not good. Thankfully our logging was able to point the finger at a particular action on the site which was causing the user to be signed off. For business and security reasons, the sign-in page had some code that detected if the user was already signed in and, if so, would immediately sign them off. The main driver was to prevent users from <em>thinking</em> that they had signed off from the application and then walk away without realising that their session was still available.</p>

<p>This didn't make sense. The user was clearly not returning to the sign-in page, but for some reason the system thought they were and hence was signing them off.</p>

<p>Emulating this at the office was proving to be impossible. We weren't able to reproduce it in <em>any</em> of our environments, and according to our help desk, none of the users claimed to be using any tools, plug-ins or add-ins which may be interfering with their sessions.</p>

<p>We searched the <a href="http://google.com/">usual</a> <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/">haunts</a> for answers, but none came up. A post here and there would get our hopes up, but we would eventually have them dashed after realising that the resolution mentioned was something that was already place. Some of the common suggestions are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Make sure that the <a title="Machine Key Explained" href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff649308.aspx#paght000007_machinekeyexplained">machine key</a> is the same across all sites in the web farm.</li>
<li>Make sure that the <a title="ASP.NET &amp; IIS Website Load Balancing" href="http://knol.google.com/k/kishore-gorjala/asp-net-iis-website-load-balancing/3jdbfde3g5y2c/3#">IIS site identifier</a> is the same across all sites in the web farm.</li>
<li>Make sure that the cookie path was set to <code>/</code> instead of having a sub-path like <code>/mysite</code>.</li>
<li>Make sure that the user's browser was accepting cookies.</li>
</ul>


<p>While point 4 was indeed a problem for some users, it wasn't the golden bullet we were looking for.</p>

<p>We spun the wheels for a few days trying to come up with potential reasons why this could be the case. One of the developers suggested that it could be an issue with applications that operate as download accelerators. This application might scrape the screen when the user has signed in, and in an effort to pre-cache the next potential click it <a title="HTTP Request Methods" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext_Transfer_Protocol#Request_methods">GET</a>s each link that it finds on screen. It turns out that this wasn't, nor couldn't, be the issue: we were not including any links to the sign-on page anywhere in the authenticated area of the site.</p>

<h2>The First Shot</h2>

<p>We decided to take a shot in the dark and remove the functionality from the sign-in page which logs the users off. Instead, we present them with a notice which tells them that they are already signed-in. After deploying to production, our users were able to sign in! We were leaping for joy, though frustrated because we didn't know why this was a problem in the first place.</p>

<p>Our joy was short-lived. The application itself provides a series of wizards that the user can utilise to perform certain tasks. <em>All</em> of the users who had problems signing in were having unexpected errors shown when using the wizards. Something was still amiss.</p>

<p>We were at a loss. So we decided to call in the cavalry: our poor users.</p>

<h2>The Site Visit</h2>

<p>We got in contact with one user, a lady who had been completely unable to interact with the site since its release, and she graciously accepted our request to pay her a visit and allow us to witness the failure in action. This proved to be a <strong>very</strong> good move as you'll soon see.</p>

<p>After the initial meet and greet, I was given access to our client's network. At first, I wanted to plug my own personal laptop in to the network to see if I could reproduce the problem without having to touch the client's machine. It wasn't to be, as  everything worked perfectly for me.</p>

<p>I requested access to the client's machine and fired up her browser of choice (<a title="Internet Explorer" href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/internet-explorer/default.aspx">yuck</a>). As soon as I hit the site, I was presented with a dialog asking for a password. Here is what it looked like:</p>

<p><a title="The Content Advisor Prompt" href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2010/10/content-advisor-prompt.png" rel="lightbox[contentadvisor]"><img style="margin-right: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px; float: left;" src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2010/10/content-advisor-prompt.png" alt="The Content Advisor Prompt" width="250" /></a>I had never seen this before, so I asked the client what it was. Her response:</p>

<blockquote><p>Oh, that's the content advisor that my husband set up. We have that enabled on all our computers so that only me and my husband can get to certain websites.</blockquote></p></blockquote>

<p><a title="Microsoft Content Advisor" href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/ie/using/howto/security/contentadv/config.mspx">Content Advisor</a>? Why had I never heard of this before? After literally <em>years</em> of building production websites, I had never once encountered this beast. Yet here it was in front of me on screen, like a smart-arse teenager giving me the bird, and according to the dates on some of the articles on the web it has been around for quite a few years.</p>

<p>I proceeded to sign in to the site and attempt to perform an action using the wizard. As expected, it failed miserably. I then asked the client to disable the Content Advisor to see if it made any difference.</p>

<p>It did. The site performed <em>flawlessly</em>.</p>

<h2>The Resolution</h2>

<p>So the Content Advisor was causing problems. But how? What was it doing behind the scenes that was preventing our users from getting the quality experience that we'd worked so hard to deliver?</p>

<p>Now that we had knowledge of the content advisor our queries to the Interwebs resulting in more revealing posts, such as one posted on <a title="IE's Content Advisor, PICS Ratings and the ASP.NET Flakey of the Day" href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/IEsContentAdvisorPICSRatingsAndTheASPNETFlakeyOfTheDay.aspx">Scott Hanselman's blog</a>. Here are some key bits of information from that post:</p>

<blockquote><p>... when Content Advisor is OFF, the interaction looks like this:<br/></p>

<p>HTTP GET /somefile.aspx<br/>
RESPONSE 200<br/>
HTTP GET /somethingelse.aspx (we did a javascript.open)<br/>
RESPONSE 302 getthisfile.aspx<br/>
HTTP GET getthisfile.aspx<br/>
RESPONSE 200<br/></p>

<p>But when <strong>Content Advisor is ON</strong>, we see this:<br/></p>

<p>HTTP GET /somefile.aspx<br/>
RESPONSE 200<br/>
HTTP GET /somethingelse.aspx (we did a javascript.open)<br/>
<strong>HTTP GET /<br/>
RESPONSE 200</strong><br/>
RESPONSE 302 getthisfile.aspx<br/>
HTTP GET getthisfile.aspx<br/>
RESPONSE 200<br/></p>

<p>...<br/></p>

<p>When the Content Advisor is ON, Internet Explorer will request '/' from a site anytime a new window is opened.</p></blockquote>

<p>As we can see from the above quote, the Content Advisor hits the root of the site on the user's behalf in an effort to scrape <a title="Platform for Internet Content Selection" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Platform_for_Internet_Content_Selection">PICS</a> information about the website.</p>

<p>According to the last point in the above quote, this will happen any time a new window is opened. Unfortunately for us, it goes deeper than that: <strong>the Content Advisor makes the browser request <code>/</code> every single time an action is invoked if it can't find sufficient PICS information for the current URL</strong>.</p>

<p>Yes, it's shit, but that's the way it works.</p>

<p>So any users which have the Content Advisor turned on will actually be hitting the site twice for every GET action they perform. This explains why the users were being signed off! Our sign-off code was being executed behind the scenes without the users being aware of it.</p>

<p>But why was it causing unexpected errors when clients were using the wizard? To answer that, we need to know about a little feature of MVC called <a title="TempData @ you've been HAACKED" href="http://haacked.com/tags/TempData/default.aspx">TempData</a>.</p>

<p>For those who don't want to click the above link, TempData is a feature of ASP.NET MVC which allows information to be persisted across post-backs to the server. A classic example is when URI <code>/Foo</code> gets invoked, and the action results in a redirect to <code>/Bar</code>. But <code>/Bar</code> requires some data that got sent to <code>/Foo</code>, so the <code>/Foo</code> action stores that data in the TempData dictionary which allows <code>/Bar</code> to get access to it during processing. It's a nifty feature, and one that we use extensively.</p>

<p>The key piece of information to remember about TempData is that it <em>only persists data across a single post-back</em>. That means that if you post back to the server once, TempData is lost unless the target action <strong>explicitly requests for it to stick around</strong>.</p>

<p>This is the deal-breaker. If <code>/Bar</code> assumes that TempData contains information from <code>/Foo</code> when it fires up then <code>/Bar</code> is going to break if the information is <em>not</em> there. Why would it not be there if a redirect happened? That's right, the f$%#ing Content Advisor!</p>

<p>It turns out that every time the Content Advisor hits the root of the site, TempData is cleared. This is obvious in hindsight because the root URI is an <a title="ASP.NET MVC Controller Overview" href="http://www.asp.net/mvc/tutorials/asp-net-mvc-controller-overview-cs">action</a> just like any other anywhere in the whole site. That action gets invoked through the same means and comes with the same caveats ... including that of TempData getting cleared unless we ask it not to. So the chain of events looked like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>User invokes a wizard via a simple click.</li>
<li>Request is set to the server for<code>/Foo</code></li>
<li><code>/Foo</code> gets executed and stores information, <code>Baz</code>, in TempData so that the next step in the wizard, <code>/Bar</code>, can get access to it.</li>
<li><code>/Foo</code> returns page content to the user.</li>
<li>The browser receives the page content from the <code>/Foo</code> action and the Content Advisor notices a lack of PICS information in the HTTP headers and META tags.</li>
<li>The Content Advisor forces the browser to make a request to <code>/</code> in an attempt to find the missing PICS information.</li>
<li>The root site action is hit and it renders the sign-on page content.</li>
<li>At the end of page content generation, the TempData dictionary notices that no requests have been made to retain any of the information across another call, and hence <strong>all of the TempData information is lost</strong>, including <code>Baz</code>.</li>
<li>The user click's "Next" in the wizard, which causes the browser to invoke the <code>/Bar</code> action on the server.</li>
<li>The server invokes <code>/Bar</code> and the first thing it does is attempt to pull <code>Baz</code> out of TempData. <code>Baz</code> ends up being null.</li>
<li>Game over, Red Rover.</li>
</ul>


<p>There are quite a few issues that were highlighted as a result, but the key one is this: <em>you can't assume that your users aren't using some form of Content Advisor which is hitting your server with unexpected requests</em>. In our case, the resolution was simple. We just had to add a couple of lines to our root action:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:csharp %}
public ActionResult SignOn()
{
  if(Request.IsAuthenticated)
  {</p>

<pre><code>// force the TempData dicionary to keep hold
// of the information it has in case this
// action is being hit by a Content Advisor.
TempData.Keep();
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  // rest of the action code
  // ...
  return View(...);
}
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The first question you might ask is: why didn't you just add PICS data to your site to prevent the Content Advisors from behaving that way? The short answer is that you can't guarantee that the Content Advisors will adhere to the "rules", especially given that there don't appear to be any.</p>

<p><a title="Platform for Internet Content Selection" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Platform_for_Internet_Content_Selection">PICS</a> has already been replaced with <a title="Protocol for Web Description Resources" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/POWDER">POWDER</a>. But POWDER doesn't appear to be used anywhere, and there's very little information around on it. Attempting to support all possible half-baked standards would result in serving up a great deal more content for the sake of a very small subset of users who actually use Content Advisors. It made much more sense to just persist TempData across one more call.</p>

<p>Bear in mind that while the Content Advisor is built-in to the Internet Options area in Windows, it's not specific to Internet Explorer. Both Chrome and Safari are affected by the Content Advisor if it is enabled!</p>

<p>So for anyone out there who is building, or has built, a public-facing website using ASP.NET MVC please bear this in mind. Keep an eye on your TempData usage, make sure that your root action persists your TempData if required, and avoid having that same action sign off your users.</p>

<p>I hope this helps someone :) Comments and feedback greatly appreciated.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Wrong Decision by the Wrong Person]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/the-wrong-decision-by-the-wrong-person/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-28T22:35:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/the-wrong-decision-by-the-wrong-person</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2010/01/pizza.jpg" title="The wrong tool." rel="lightbox"><img src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2010/01/pizza.jpg" alt="The wrong tool." title="The wrong tool." style="float:right; margin-left:5px; margin-bottom:5px;"  width="150"/></a>There is one thing about my industry that I still find truly amazing (and not in a good way). This is despite the fact that it has happened to me so many times that you think I'd be used to it! I'm talking about non-technical people making technical decisions.</p>

<p>For some reason, it's a very common practice for those people who don't have expertise in a certain field to make decisions for people working in that field. The best example I can think of off the top of my head is the answer to the question: <em>"Which technology should we use?"</em></p>

<p>Let me take a step back in time for a moment.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I applied for a job with a certain company (which shall remain nameless) that was looking for a number of C#/.NET developers of a certain level of experience. After confirming an interview date and time, I turned up to find myself facing a panel of 3 interviewers. One of those people held a technical position, though I found out later that the position he held was self-appointed and certainly not an indication of the person's level of technical knowledge or expertise. The other two were in non-technical positions.</p>

<p>During the interview we had the usual discussions and questions around technial knowledge, depth of understanding of certain areas of the .NET framework, views and approaches to dealing with people in teams, agile experience, etc. It all went very well. At the end of the interview I was given my chance to ask a few questions. The main one I wanted to ask was <em>"Why did you decide to use .NET for this project?"</em></p>

<p>For the record, the <em>previous</em> version of the system was written using an older Microsoft technology stack. The decision had been made to go with .NET for this new version. Can you see the correlation?</p>

<p>The answer was quite stunning. The only reason the project was using .NET was because the previous version was a Microsoft-based solution.</p>

<p>The first thing I thought was "surely that can't be it?". As a matter of fact, that wasn't the <em>only</em> reason for it, but it was the <em>main</em> reason. The decision wasn't made by a technical person, it was made by someone in upper management.</p>

<p>Scary huh!?</p>

<p>In my personal opinion, there is one particular technology that I think would have done a much better job of solving this particular problem, and it's not a Microsoft solution. It's not a Sun solution, or any other mainstream option for that matter. In my view, <strong>Erlang</strong> would have been perfect.</p>

<p>I don't think that a company like that would have ever even considered Erlang as a viable option. Mainly for two reasons. The first is that the amount of skilled Erlang developers available on the East Coast of Australia is extremely small. The second is fear of the unknown/non-mainstream tech. That is, companies like to go with what other companies are going with.</p>

<p>The crazy thing about this scenario is that management go to market to hire people who are domain experts, and then proceed to tell them which technologies to use. Surely you would be better off hiring people to know how to solve problem X really well, and then listen to what they have to say about the technology stack that should be put in place? No, not in this industry. Probably not in my lifetime either!</p>

<p>So if you're a non-tech person leading a team of techies, please PLEASE listen to what they have to say. Ask them what they think is the right approach and the right toolset. Don't take control of the technical decisions. Let them do what you hired them to do: Solve the problem, and use the right tool for the job. If they don't know the answer, or the answer is always the same, then you've got the wrong developers.</p>

<p>Thanks for listening :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Don't Need Your Frickin' Framework!]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/i-dont-need-your-frickin-framework/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-13T14:09:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/i-dont-need-your-frickin-framework</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2009/04/scaffold_fail.jpg" title="Scaffold Fail"><img src="http://buffered.io/uploads/2009/04/scaffold_fail.jpg" alt="Scaffold Fail" title="Scaffold Fail" width="200" style="float: right; margin-left: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px;" /></a>How many companies have you worked with/for that have their own framework? How many have been in the process of developing their own framework? How many have been in the process of <strong>re</strong>developing their own framework? How many have taken another framework and <del>hacked</del> improved it?</p>

<p>When I attempt to answer the questions listed above, I start to shiver. I feel the need to burn my clothes and take a very long shower.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In the early days of my career, frameworks were few and far between. These days it is no longer the case. An alarming number of companies are carrying the burden of their own frameworks. A huge number of private and public sector organisations are <em>currently paying people to write new frameworks</em>! For some reason, many nave project managers and team leads feel the need to invest a great deal of time and <abbr title="Cash">moolah</abbr> into building the next-generation, latest-and-greatest, all-singing-all-dancing, cover-every-possible-web-and-rich-client-case framework before they start to do what they're being paid to do: <strong>solve a business problem</strong>.</p>

<p>The last job I worked on was one of those places. On my first day I was told that the project team (which at that point was just 2 of the 6 developers) were building a new framework. They were also building a code generator that used this framework. This dynamic duo of programs would be used in conjunction with each other to build any kind of application under the sun. It would solve all of the issues without the developer having to think, all while making poverty history.</p>

<p>What a joke. The code generator was never finished and the framework was never used. The money that was intended to be burned while <em>adding more features to an existing application</em> disappeared in a blur of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenfield_project" title="">Greenfield</a> over-engineering of a framework that simply <strong>was not required</strong>.</p>

<p>This kind of problem happens so much these days, and it's just appalling. What I want to say is: <em>I am <a href="http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=frickin" title="">frickin'</a> tired of it!</em></p>

<p>The example I mentioned above is probably the worst I've seen for a while. I'd love to go into a fair bit of depth to uncover some "interesting" features of the framework, but it's not worth it. I <em>would</em> like to highlight just a few points about it though:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It was based on <a href="http://www.lhotka.net/cslanet/" title="CSLA">CSLA</a>, which is already a rather large framework that attempts to do way too much via an enormous amount of code. The author decided that some parts of CSLA weren't good enough and hence needed to be "improved". The "improvements" were atrocious.</li>
<li>It was supposed to be Open Source, but as far as I'm aware it never made it onto the Web, hence I can't point you at it.</li>
<li>In some areas of code, you were required to invoke functions through a generic <kbd>MessagePortal</kbd> helper object which invoked the required function via reflection after attempting to infer a stack of unnecessary information. This was interesting, as you knew what you needed to call. But you still had to pass in function names as string parameters, hence losing knowledge, and wait for the framework to regain that knowledge by inspecting the code at runtime. Even though the excessive use of reflection was &lt;sarcasm&gt;an obvious win&lt;/sarcasm&gt;, we also copped the added bonus of having another 35 (yes, that's right <strong>35</strong>) function calls appearing in our call-stack.</li>
<li>Those developers who attempted to use it were bitten constantly by esoteric and undocumented pitfalls in the design.</li>
<li>It took around 3 times longer during development to do the "basics" (such as create objects and have them load from a DB). This is compared to using no framework and loading objects manually via ADO.</li>
<li>It was unable to load any form of object graph.</li>
<li>It not only leaked database connections every time you made a database call, it leaked <em>two extra connections</em> during start-up while it attempts to read some database information, such as schema, into memory.</li>
<li>The code generator was written in such a way that the first half of the generator would be used to generate the other half (epic fail)!</li>
<li>The author wasn't able to use it.</li>
</ul>


<p>I hence conclude that this framework was a large, unwieldy, bloated, over-engineered, slow and riddled with design flaws. This is all for something that was actually totally unnecessary. Why? ...</p>

<p>.. because this was <strong>"The Framework" v2.0!</strong> Yup, it was the second version. The first was also a dog's breakfast, but at least it was finished.</p>

<p>So what's my point? Am I trying to say that use of <em>any</em> framework is bad? Having helper libraries and well-designed platforms to build on are an epic fail?</p>

<p>Most definitely not. What I am saying is this: there are people out there with minds immeasurably superior to ours who have already done a better job of solving this problem. Stop writing your own frameworks. Stop writing code generators. There are already options out there.</p>

<p>So to all of you wannabe framework developers: stop what you're doing. You're wasting cash and not adding value. We've already got a framework. It's called <strong>Microsoft .NET</strong>. Now get out of the way and let me use it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
