<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ASM | OJ's perspective]]></title>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/categories/asm/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://buffered.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-28T13:31:42+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://buffered.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[OJ Reeves]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reversing DirectX &amp; Blowfish]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/reversing-directx-blowfish/"/>
    <updated>2007-04-09T06:31:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/reversing-directx-blowfish</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This tutorial has been on the boil for quite a while.  I got close to nailing the problem late last month, but didn&rsquo;t end up finding the time to finish it until this weekend.  This tutorial is a solution to another Crackme, but this time it&rsquo;s really not for the faint-hearted.  Information on reversing fullscreen <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/directx/" title="DirectX">DirectX (Direct3D)</a> applications and playing around with <a href="http://www.schneier.com/blowfish.html" title="Blowfish">Blowfish</a> can be found in this tutorial, and it&rsquo;s a bit of a mind-job &ndash; it also weighs in at nearly 40 pages (with some nice pictures thrown in)!</p>

<p>Take a look at the <a href="/uploads/2007/04/silverdxcrackme1.zip">Crackme</a> and then <a href="/uploads/2007/04/Silver-DirectX-Solution-TheColonial.zip">my solution</a>. Enjoy.</p>

<h3>Update: 9th Feb 2012</h3>

<p>This tutorial was originally posted and hosted on <a href="http://www.crackmes.de/">Crackmes.de</a> alongside the crackme itself. Unfortunately Crackems.de had been taken offline for quite a while for legal reasons and hence the tutorial wasn&rsquo;t available there.</p>

<p>Thanks to issues with webhosts and backup failures, this tutorial was completely unavailable for a long time. Thankfully that site is back up now and I finally have a copy of the tutorial again.</p>

<p>You can still reference the material over on that <a href="http://www.crackmes.de/users/silver/silvers_dx_crackme_1/">site</a>, but I have decided to host a copy of it here as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another Lesson in Software Reversing]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/another-lesson-in-software-reversing/"/>
    <updated>2007-03-08T21:10:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/another-lesson-in-software-reversing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.iitac.org/" title="IITAC.org" target="_blank"><img src="http://certification.iitac.org/templates/default/images/HeaderIcon.png" class="InlineImageLeft" alt="IITAC.org" /></a>Yes, you can (most probably) consider this to be a fairly regular segment from this point on :) As I said before I&rsquo;ve always been partial to RCE, and I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ll ever get sick of it.  Today&rsquo;s installment is another tutorial that I felt shouldn&rsquo;t be published.  The reason is because it&rsquo;s a tutorial on how to solve an example reversing challenge for the <a href="http://certification.iitac.org/goto.php?target=cat_384&client_id=iitac" title="" target="_blank">IITAC online RCE adacemy</a>, and I generally don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s a good move to show other people how to do this stuff when they can get certified for it. However, this is just a <em>training</em> example so I think I&rsquo;m safe.</p>

<p>The challenge consists of a few tasks:<ol><li>Removing a nag-screen</li><li>Finding a hard-coded serial number</li><li>Finding a valid name/serial combination</li><li>Writing a key generator</li></ol>You&rsquo;ll notice from the tutorial that the full source code is included written in 32-bit ASM.  Again, I would appreciate the feedback on the quality from anyone who wishes to give it (that includes you Alister ;) ) as I&rsquo;m always looking to improve what I write.</p>

<p>You can grab it from <a href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2007/03/01-course-splish-2.zip" title="Course 01 - Splish 2 reversing solution">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Reversing Tutorial]]></title>
    <link href="http://buffered.io/posts/a-reversing-tutorial/"/>
    <updated>2007-03-03T00:24:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://buffered.io/posts/a-reversing-tutorial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a long time I&rsquo;ve been interested in the lovely and exciting art of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reverse_engineering" title="Reverse Engineering" target="_blank">Reverse Code Engineering</a> (RCE) and on more than one occasion I&rsquo;ve been sucked in to spending hours and hours delving through pages of ASM code searching for the answer.</p>

<p>Today is no different. With Amy feeling pretty crook due to a nasty headache, I thought I&rsquo;d retire to my PC and do something quiet that I haven&rsquo;t done for ages. So I downloaded a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crackme" title="Crackme" target="_blank">crackme</a> from <a href="http://www.crackmes.de/" title="Crackmes.de" target="_blank">Crackmes.de</a> and started reversing. After nailing the problem to the wall, I decided to unleash my learnings on the world via a tutorial. When coders go through the rigmarole of producing these little apps for people like me to play with, it seems only fair that I give back with a bit of information on how I broke their protection scheme. Not just that, but it gives other wannabe-reversers something to read and learn from to.</p>

<p>For those of you who are interested in reading and learning the basics, feel free to <a href="http://buffered.io/uploads/2007/03/nts-crackme10-solution-thecolonial.zip" title="Solution to a Crackme">download the goods</a>. Any feedback is appreciated (but only if it&rsquo;s good :D ).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
